[Music]
is it possible to ameliorate chronic
kidney disease using a whole food
plant-based diet in my last video on
kidney disease I talked about how
randomizing people to cut just around 10
grams of protein from their daily diet
could cut their risk of dialysis and
death by a whopping
77% that was cutting protein across the
board but while animal-based protein
ingestion and meat Dairy and egg white
protein ingestion promotes an acidic
environment in the kidneys inflammation
and stresses the kidneys to what's
called hyperfiltration mode plant-based
protein can be alkaline producing and
anti-inflammatory and contain kidney
protective properties so what if you
have kidney patients eat a plant
dominant low protein diet abbreviated
adorably as Play-Doh I guess for plant
dominant if you fashion up a plant-based
diet index score where you get points
for healthy plant foods and get points
deducted for eating animal Foods those
with serious kidney disease with higher
scores were found to have lower systemic
inflammation but does that actually
translate into living longer life
apparently so even a 10% increase in the
proportion of plant-based protein was
associated with a significant reduction
in all cause mortality even just eating
more servings of fruits and vegetables
like two a day compared to two a week is
linked to living
longer without fully functioning kidneys
there are concerns about phosphorus and
potassium overload though on a
plant-based diet but the phosphorus and
plant-based Foods is not as much of a
problem as the phosphorus additives in
processed in animal foods and the risk
of potassium overload from plant-based
diets appears overstated and not
supported by the evidence but you don't
know about ameliorating chronic kidney
disease using a whole food plant-based
diet on until you put it to the test
here's a case report of a 69y old man
with type 2 diabetes high blood pressure
and stage three chronic kidney disease
resulting in elevated phosphorus and
potassium in the blood interested in
changing his diet to improve his medical
condition That's my kind of patient he
was on 12 different medications eating a
diet that may actually be slightly
better than the average American some
whole grains and beans but then his
doctor advised to try eating Whole Food
plant-based so yeah you know oatmeal
with fruit and flax beans and greens
whole wheat spaghetti and veggies fruit
to snacks Cel to eat as much as he
wanted from Whole healthy foods no carb
counting no calorie counting no portion
size restriction improving the quality
of food rather than restricting the
quantity of food he adopted the whole
food plant-based diet packed with carbs
yet rapidly reduced his insulin
requirements by more than 50% and
subsequently saw Improvement m ments in
weight blood pressure and cholesterol
because eating healthy can have such a
rapid effect on improving your body's
insulin sensitivity immediate
adjustments and Insulin dosing were made
within 4 days his insulin dose was able
to be reduced from roughly 210 units of
insulin a day down to 70 units daily and
an oral blood sugar lowering medication
had to be stopped due to rapidly
improving blood sugar he also was able
to stop his carvol hydrochlorizide
amlodipine acidic liptin Within the
first two months due to improving blood
pressure and blood sugars his insulin
dose was steadily titrated downward his
prostatin dose was cut in half and he
lost about 50 lbs okay so what happened
to his stage three kidney failure he was
no longer in stage three kidney failure
doctors watching this will understand
what all these numbers mean here's a
graph of his GFR which is a measure of
kidney function declining for years
before shooting up after he started
eating healthy he experienced an
increase in estimated GFR of 73%
suggesting that the Improvement in
estimated kidney function was greater
than what would be expected from weight
loss alone for example lose about 60 PBS
from bariatric surgery you only get
about 12 to 15% boost bottom line for
individuals with chronic kidney disease
especially those with obesity
hypertension or diabetes a strict all
you care to eat whole food plant-based
diet May confer significant benefit I
mean apart from the kidney specific
outcomes overall mortality is
significantly lower among kidney
patients who eat more plants and that's
critical because most kidney patients
don't even make it to dialysis because
they die first most often from
cardiovascular
disease let's hear from the
patient at the outset it seemed like
this was going to be a difficult and
restrictive way to eat but I began
feeling different almost immediately we
had to decrease my insulin after one day
it seemed like almost overnight I had
more energy than I'd had in years weight
I've been trying to lose for a decade
began dropping off as the weight came
off I felt lighter more able to move my
body again this lifestyle change has
been the greatest gift I've ever
received I'm off most of my medications
I've lost over 70 pounds and I've
regained control over my health I feel
empowered by this lifestyle change I
finally feel like I'm in charge of my
health and not just an unlucky victim
Shuffling from one specialist to the
next my only regret was that I didn't
know about this
[Music]
sooner for